A Guide to the Marie M. Jenkins Papers, 1951-1979: SC 0180
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Marie M. Jenkins Papers,
1951-1979
Special Collections, James Madison University
Marie Magdalen Jenkins, 1906-
SC 0180
1.65 cubic feet; 5 boxes
This collection consists of five boxes containing mostly Dr. Jenkins' research notes on planarians during the years 1963-1974. A few folders contain records and correspondence relating to her teaching and research at James Madison University and other professional activities from 1959 to 1979.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Jenkins donated these papers to the library in September 1987.
Bio/Historical Note
Marie Magdalen Jenkins was born September 26, 1906 in Eldorado, Illinois. After attending Phillips University, she taught in elementary and secondary schools in Oklahoma until 1942. At that time she took vows as Sister Mary Scholastica in the Benedictine Order. She completed her Master's degree at Catholic University in 1951, and taught or worked in Catholic schools until 1957, when she left the Order and entered the University of Oklahoma. In the late 1950s and early 1960s she taught zoology there while completing her Ph.D. Dr. Jenkins came to the Biology Department of Madison College (now James Madison University) in 1962, and retired from there in 1975.
For thirty years before she retired, Dr. Jenkins conducted original research on planarians (flatworms), particularly the relationship between aging and reproduction. She discovered that, contrary to previous thought, planarians do not live forever, and she gained an international reputation as an expert on the animals. For several years in the early 1970s, Dr. Jenkins raised and sold planarians for laboratory use. In the late 1970s, an Italian researcher named a new planarian species after her (Dugesia jenkinsae), after identifying it among specimens she had sent him.
Although she had been contributing to the professional science literature, starting in the late 1960s Dr. Jenkins began to pursue seriously a lifelong interest in writing for a broader audience. In 1969 her first science book for children, Moon jelly swims through the sea, was published, followed by: Animals without parents (1970; The Curious mollusks (1972); Embryos and how they develop (1975); Kangaroos, opossums and other marsupials (1975); Goats, sheep and how they live (1978); and Deer, moose, elk and their family (1979). Several of these were listed in Bowker's second edition of Best books for children, in 1981. All are available in Special Collections.
Scope and Content
This collection consists mostly of Dr. Jenkins' research notes on planarians during the years 1963-1974. A few folders contain records and correspondence relating to her teaching and research at James Madison University and other professional activities from 1959 to 1979.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: 1. Correspondence, records, & publications. 2. Planarian Research. The order imposed by the creator was maintained.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Planaria -- Research; Invertebrates -- Research; Planaria as laboratory animals; Dugesia dorotocephala -- Research; Dugesia dorotocephala -- Physiology; Dugesia dorotocephala -- Reproduction; Regeneration (Biology); Physiology, Comparative; Dugesia dorotocephala -- Metabolism
Genre and Form Terms:
Letters (correspondence)
- Series 1: Correspondence, records, publications, 1951-1979
  - JMU correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - JMU correspondence, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - JMU official records, 1963-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NIH other grants, corresp. records, 1957-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - VA Acad. of Sciences corres. records, 1963-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 6 Book correspondence, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Planarian correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 1951-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Planarian research, 1963-1974
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - I series (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - I series (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - II series (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - III series (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - IV series (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - V series (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - V series (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - V series (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - V series (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - VI series (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - VI series (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - VI series (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - VII series (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - VIII-IX series (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - X series (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - A series (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - F5 series (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - B series (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - B series (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - B series (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - B series (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - B series (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous series, mostly crosses (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Aging (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Body fission, sexual, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Data, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Latitude planarians, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Phosphohexose (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Pooled deviation (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Regeneration/aging - cocoons, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Tables - fission, sexual, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - D series (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - D series (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - F3 Series (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - W series (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - W series (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - W series (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Z series (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Moon phase (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Texas (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 3 notebooks (Box 5)
  - Worm Runner's Digest, 1959-1964 (Box 5)